{"tossups": [{"question": "This body of water was the destination of Zachariah Gillam\u2019s ship<em> Nonsuch</em>. Henry Green and Robert Juet led a mutiny in this body of water, casting the captain of the<em> Discovery</em> and his son adrift to their death. The area around this body of water was once called Rupert\u2019s Land. A company named for this body of water controlled the fur trade in colonial-era Canada. For ten points, name this Canadian body of water named for the British explorer Henry.", "answer": "<b> Hudson</b> Bay", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "At his villa in Samoussy, Carloman is said to have died either of natural causes or of a particularly bad instance of this phenomenon, possibly the result of poisoned tea. Another death of this type may have been the result of uncharacteristically heavy drinking while planning to sack Constantinople; that 453 AD event occurred while its victim was with Ildico on his wedding night. For ten points, name this condition that is said to have killed Attila the Hun.", "answer": "<b> nosebleed</b>s (accept<b> epistaxis</b>; accept<b> choking on blood</b>; prompt on choking)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A 1999 biography of this man by Dava Sobel concerns his relationship with his daughter, whom he sent to a convent. This man outlined his mathematical methods in<em> The Assayer</em>, which wrongly disputed the nature of comets. In another work by this man, Simplicio represents the church in a heretical book that was banned in 1633.<em> Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems</em> was written by, for ten points, what Italian scientist who was brought before the Inquisition for supporting heliocentrism?", "answer": "<b> Galileo Galilei</b> (accept either or both names)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This politician secretly profited as a co-founder of the Win or Lose oil company, and largely was able to control the governor of his state, Oscar K. Allen. Dentist Carl Weiss murdered this man, who proposed a net wealth tax to fund redistribution of resources in a plan whose vision was \u201cevery man a king.\u201d The\u201cShare Our Wealth\u201d program was touted by, for ten points, what fiery Depression-era Louisiana senator nicknamed \u201cKingfish?\u201d", "answer": "Huey Pierce<b> Long</b>, Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In the chapter \u201cA Picture Contest,\u201d an official tries to marry his daughter to a holder of this position by ordering fantastic displays of artwork. A person in this position exiles his half-brother to the coast when the man is caught in an embarrassing affair. A holder of this position becomes blind after having obsessive dreams of his father. Kiritsubo, Suzaku, and Reizei all hold this position in a Heian period novel by Murasaki Shikibu. For ten points, Genji serves as an official in the court of what type of leader?", "answer": "<b> emperor of Japan</b> (prompt on partial answers, like \u201cemperor\u201d or \u201cleader of Japan;\u201d do not accept shogun or other terms)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "An artwork comprised of these objects shows four white squares and a white tree on a purple background. A term for these objects provides the alternate name for the Tawagonshi Treaty. Sets of these objects were used to convey rank and station within the Iroquois Confederacy, and they comprise the Hiawatha Belt. A popular legend holds that Peter Minuit bought the island of Manhattan with 24 dollars worth of these objects. Wampum are comprised of, for ten points, what objects made of shells and displayed on threads or strings?", "answer": "<b> bead</b>s (accept<b> wampum</b> before mentioned; accept<b> shell</b>s before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This island\u2019s reconquest was led by the Hauteville family, whose Roger II elevated it to a kingdom. Pressing the claim of his wife Constance of Hohenstaufen, Peter III of Aragon was invited to conquer this island during its namesake Vespers. After the War of the Quadruple Alliance, the Habsburgs exchanged Sardinia for this island with Victor Amadeus II of Savoy. For ten points, name this island that Garibaldi\u2019s Expedition of the Thousand unified with Italy.", "answer": "<b> Sicily</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Members of the \u201cSouthern Bloc\u201d opposed this bill, which was signed by Lyndon Johnson in the presence of Martin Luther King. For ten points, name this landmark anti-discrimination bill.", "answer": "<b> Civil Rights</b> Act of 1964 (accept answers that use Act, Bill, and/or Law; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1906, this venue hosted a silver anniversary lecture in which Mark Twain spoke to raise funds for the Tuskegee Institute. Duke Ellington wrote a three-movement suite depicting African-American history, <em>Black, Brown, and Beige</em>, for his 1943 debut at this venue, which hosted a sold-out 1938 concert that marked the first time jazz was played in a \u201cserious\u201d setting. The New York Philharmonic moved to the Lincoln Center from, for ten points, what legendary concert venue built by a namesake steel magnate in 1891?", "answer": "<b> Carnegie Hall</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "The behavior of this organization was at the heart of the<em> Katz</em> and<em> Olmstead</em> Supreme Court cases. A former employee of this organization, Robert Hanssen, is currently serving fifteen consecutive life sentences in jail. Other employees of this organization included Helen Gandy and Clyde Tolson, who were close advisers of its longtime director. For ten points, name this American domestic police organization headed for decades by J. Edgar Hoover.", "answer": "<b> Federal Bureau of Investigation</b> (accept<b> FBI</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "When this man\u2019s son used the pseudonym John Clarke, the confusion led the Prince of Conti to insult him. George Monck fought alongside this ruler at the Battle of Dunbar and was made commander-in-chief of Scotland. John Lambert wrote the<em> Instrument of Government</em> during this man\u2019s rule. After the siege of Drogheda, this man ordered the New Model Army to spare no one. For ten points, name this Lord Protector of England who signed Charles I\u2019s death warrant after the English Civil Wars.", "answer": "Oliver<b> Cromwell</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This site\u2019s inner gallery, or Bakan, is speculated to have been flooded as a form of art depicting the supposed center of the universe. The Preah Poan, or Hall of a Thousand Gods, within this complex, once contained numerous images of the Buddha. This complex was built in Yasodharapura [yaso-dara-pura] as a depiction of Mount Meru during the reign of Suryavarman II, a ruler of the Khmer Empire. For ten points, name this 400-acre temple complex of Cambodia.", "answer": "<b> Angkor Wat</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The first leader of this empire consolidated the tribes under him with the help of the Ayar brothers. Another man led this empire after his brother, Ninan Cuyochi, died of smallpox. A Dominican named Vincent de Valverde was spared by a man who usurped this empire\u2019s throne after ruling over Quito; that man was defeated at the 1532 Battle of Cajamarca and was the half-brother of its earlier leader Hu\u00b4ascar. For ten points, name this South American empire that was conquered by Francisco Pizarro.", "answer": "<b> Inca</b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A central aspect of this document supposedly arose out of one man\u2019s gratitude for being cured of a\u201cmighty and filthy\u201d disease. Reginald Pecocke arrived at the same conclusion of the most famous person who studied this document. That man realized that the author of this document would never use the word \u201csatrap,\u201d and thus declared this work to be a forgery. Lorenzo Valla debunked, for ten points, what document addressed to Sylvester I in which an Emperor supposedly gave Rome to the Pope?", "answer": "<b> Donation of Constantine</b> (accept<b> Constantio Donatini</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A surgeon named Mary Walker is the only woman to receive this award. 864 of these items that were later revoked were awarded by Edwin Stanton to volunteers who stayed on</b> <b>past their (+)</b> <b>enlistment end-date. Buffalo Bill Cody received one of these awards as a</b> <b>scout in the Indian Wars, one of the few (*)</b> civilians to be given it. The most common action cited when bestowing this award has been falling on a grenade. The President of the United States personally awards, for ten points, what highest military decoration, given for acts of valor?", "answer": "<b> Medal of Honor</b> (accept<b> Congressional Medal of Honor</b>, but do not accept or prompt on \u201cCongressional Medal\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A sports minister from this country received copies of</b><em><b> The Art of the Deal</b></em><b> and</b><em><b> Where\u2019s </b><b>Waldo?</b></em><b> while meeting with an ambassador in 2017. James Clapper\u2019s visit to this country</b> <b>helped secure the release of Todd (+)</b> <b>Miller in 2014. Government authorities from this</b> <b>country claimed that botulism, not torture, led to the death of a visitor who had stolen a propaganda poster, (*) </b> Otto Warmbier. Journalists Laura Ling and Euna Lee were arrested in this country in 2009, but pardoned after a visit by Bill Clinton. Dennis Rodman has made several controversial visits to, for ten points, what reclusive Asian country?", "answer": "<b> North Korea</b> (or<b> Democratic People\u2019s Republic of Korea</b>; accept<b> DPRK</b>; prompt on Korea; do not prompt on Republic of Korea)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>In this empire\u2019s \u201cdark age,\u201d its split territory was ruled by two kings, Gotarzes I and Orodes I. This empire\u2019s forces once attempted to depose Tigranes [tig-RAH-nays] the Great by invading Armenia. The Arsacid dynasty ruled this empire, whose (+) cavalry perfected a tactic of feigning retreat only to suddenly turn around and launch a storm of arrows, known as its namesake \u201cshot.\u201d That tactic was used by this empire\u2019s general, Surena, to deal a devastating defeat to the invading armies of (*)</b> Marcus Crassus at the Battle of Carrhae. For ten points, name this ancient Iranian empire that preceded the Sassanids.", "answer": "<b> Parthia</b>n Empire (accept<b> Arsacid</b> Empire before \u201cArsacid\u201d is read; prompt on Iran or Persia before \u201cIranian\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>In this film, India spreads rumors of infidelity after spying her brother embracing the protagonist, who tricks Frank Kennedy into marrying her. In this film, Bonnie Blue dies attempting to jump over a fence on horseback. A barbecue is held at (+) Twelve Oaks near the beginning of this film, which is, after adjusting for (*)</b> inflation, the highest grossing film of all-time. Ashley Wilkes is loved by the protagonist of this film, in which Clark Gable played Rhett Butler. For ten points, name this 1939 film focusing on Scarlett O\u2019Hara\u2019s struggles during the Civil War.", "answer": "<b> Gone With the Wind</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "<b>This ruler employed the sculptor Bek, and the blocks used for construction during this ruler\u2019s reign were known as</b><em><b> talatats</b></em><b>. This man\u2019s correspondence with Tushratta, king of the Mittani, discussed his marriage with Tadukhipa; those (+) letters were recovered by Jorgen Alexander Knudtzon on clay tablets at Amarna. Thutmose sculpted a bust of this man\u2019s wife, (*)</b> Nefertiti, and this ruler was succeeded by his supposed son, Smenkhkare. For ten points, name this father of Tutankhamen, a pharaoh who venerated the sun disc Aten.", "answer": "<b> Akhenaten</b> (or<b> Amenhotep IV</b>; accept<b> Amenophis IV</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Diodorus Siculus described this structure\u2019s layers of lead, brick, and bitumen coal as a means of water retention. In the writings of Strabo and Quintus Curtius Rufus, this monument was supplied with water using an Archimedes screw. This structure</b> <b>was built on the (+)</b> <b>request of the daughter of Cyaxares [sigh-AX-ar-eez], but</b> <b>mention of it is curiously absent in Herodotus\u2019 history of its city. This structure was possibly built to (*)</b> simulate a mountain covered with forests for the Median Queen Amytis by King Nebuchadnezzar. For ten points, name this possibly mythical tiered structure covered with trees and vines in Babylon.", "answer": "<b> Hanging Gardens</b> of Babylon", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}